Mo Tiwari

mohittiwarinyc@gmail.com | (415) 234 - 3187 motiwari.com | U.S. Citizen



SUMMARY:

I am currently at OpenAI as a Member of Technical Staff. I work on deep learning models and deploying models at scale. I previously completed a Ph.D. in Computer Science at Stanford University, worked at Facebook, worked as an early employee at a startup acquired for \$800MM, and completed my B.S. in Mathematics and Physics at Caltech.

EDUCATION:

Stanford University, Stanford, CA Ph.D. in Computer Science Thesis: "Accelerating Machine Learning Algorithms with Adaptive Sampling" Areas: deep learning, randomized algorithms Advisors: Sebastian Thrun and Chris Piech Received over \$800,000 in fellowships	GPA: 4.2+	2017 – 2023
M.S. in Computer Science (completed during Ph.D.)	GPA: 4.2+	June 2019
California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA Top 5% of Graduating Class (Top 15 students)	GPA: 4.0+	2010 – 2013
B.S. in Mathematics with Honors B.S. in Physics with Honors	GPA: 4.0+ GPA: 4.0+	June 2013 June 2013
Columbia University – Columbia College, New York, NY	GPA: 4.0+	2009 – 2010
INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE:		

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE:

MEMBER OF TECHNICAL STAFF - OPENAI, INC.

2024 - Present

- Developed and deployed deep learning models at ChatGPT- and API-scale throughput
- Developed risk models that saved OpenAl a substantial amount in revenue (exact numbers under NDA)
- Managed an intern who received and accepted a fulltime offer

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, TECHNICAL LEAD - FACEBOOK, INC.

2015 - 2017

- Technical lead of the team building ThreatExchange, Facebook's platform for sharing cybersecurity information
- Led product and feature development through 5 major releases that grew the number of enterprise customers from 92 to 500+
- Managed 3 interns who received and accepted fulltime offers

SECURITY RESEARCH SCIENTIST - EXPANSE, INC. (acquired for \$800MM) 2014 - 2015

- As the fifth fulltime employee, performed the first systematic, continuous, and Internetscale capture and analysis of device data and security vulnerabilities
- Built backend and frontend infrastructure to help analysts understand terabytes of prostitution advertisements and uncover human trafficking
- Work indirectly led to arrests of dozens of human traffickers and rescue of victims

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS:

- **Mo Tiwari***, Donghyun Lee. "Prompt Infection: LLM-to-LLM Prompt Injection within Multi-Agent Systems." Preprint.
- **Mo Tiwari***, Adarsh Kumarappan*, Peiyang Song, Robert Joseph George, Chaowei Xiao, Anima Anandkumar. "LeanAgent: Lifelong Learning for Formal Theorem Proving." <u>Preprint</u>.
- Tavor Baharav*, Ryan Kang*, Colin Sullivan*, Mo Tiwari, Eric Sager Luxenberg, David Tse, Mert Pilanci "Adaptive Sampling for Efficient Softmax Approximation." Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2024.
- Je-Yong Lee*, Donghyun Lee*, Genghan Zhang, Mo Tiwari, Azalia Mirhoseini. "CATS: Contextually-Aware Thresholding for Sparsity in Large Language Models." <u>Conference on Language Modeling</u> (COLM) 2024.
- **Mo Tiwari**, Ryan Kang*, Je-Yong Lee*, Donghyun Lee*, Chris Piech, Ilan Shomorony, Sebastian Thrun, Martin Zhang. "Faster Maximum Inner Product Search in High Dimensions." International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2024.
- Mo Tiwari*, Colin Sullivan*, Sebastian Thrun. "MAPTree: Beating 'Optimal' Decision Trees with Bayesian Decision Trees." <u>AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</u> (AAAI) 2024.
 Selected for Oral Presentation: top 9.5% / 2.3% of accepted / submitted papers
- **Mo Tiwari**, Ryan Kang, Donghyun Lee, Sebastian Thrun, Ilan Shomorony, Martin Zhang. "BanditPAM++: Faster *k*-medoids Clustering." <u>Neural Information Processing Systems</u> (*NeurIPS*) 2023.
- Mo Tiwari*, Guy Blanc*, Jane Lange*, Chirag Pabbaraju*, Colin Sullivan*, Li-Yang Tan* (listed alphabetically). "Harnessing the Power of Choices in Decision Tree Learning." Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2023.
- Aarohi Srivastava, ..., Mo Tiwari, ..., Ziyi Wu (444 authors, listed alphabetically). "Beyond the Imitation Game: Quantifying and Extrapolating the Capabilities of Language Models." <u>Transactions on Machine Learning Research</u> (TMLR) 2023.
- Yoshua Bengio*, Salem Lahlou*, Tristan Deleu*, Edward Hu, Mo Tiwari, Emmanuel Bengio.
 "GFlowNet Foundations." <u>Journal of Machine Learning Research</u> (JMLR) 2023.
- Kausthubh D. Dhole, ..., Mo Tiwari, ..., Yue Zhang (122 authors). "NL-Augmenter: A Framework for Task-Sensitive Natural Language Augmentation." Northern European Journal of Language Technology (NEJLT) 2023.
- Mo Tiwari, Ryan Kang, Je-Yong Lee, Chris Piech, Ilan Shomorony, Sebastian Thrun, Martin Zhang. "MABSplit: Faster Forest Training Using Multi-Armed Bandits." Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2022.

- Qi Liu, ..., Mo Tiwari, ..., Shiew-Mei Huang (13 authors). "Landscape Analysis of the Application of Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning in Regulatory Submissions for Drug Development from 2016 to 2021." <u>Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics</u> 2022.
- Mo Tiwari, Martin Zhang, James Mayclin, Sebastian Thrun, Chris Piech, Ilan Shomorony.
 "BanditPAM: Almost Linear Time k-medoids Clustering via Multi-Armed Bandits."
 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020.
- Mo Tiwari, ..., Charles C. Lin (13 authors). "Differentiation of Active Corneal Infections from Healed Scars Using Deep Learning." Journal paper in <u>Ophthalmology</u>. Best Poster Award at associated conference, American Academy of Ophthalmology (AAO) 2020.
- Serhat Arslan, **Mo Tiwari**, Chris Piech. "Using Google Search Trends to Estimate Global Patterns in Learning." <u>ACM Learning</u> @ Scale (L@S) 2020.

OPEN SOURCE CONTRIBUTIONS:

• BanditPAM: https://github.com/motiwari/BanditPAM. Primary author, 600+ stars.

A high-performance Python package, written in C++, that implements the algorithm from our NeurIPS 2020 paper and is pip-installable via pip install banditpam.

TEACHING AND MENTORSHIP:

- Course Assistant for Client-Side Internet Technologies (CS 193C): Graded assignments, provided feedback, and answered questions for over 100 students each quarter during the summers of 2020 and 2021. Recruited top students for research projects.
- **EDGE Mentor:** Mentored three early Ph.D. students in Computer Science at Stanford University through a formal, funded appointment.
- **Ph.D. Student Mentor:** Managed over a dozen undergraduate, M.S., and junior Ph.D. students at Stanford University. Upward reviews available upon request.

ADDITIONAL RESEARCH EXPERIENCE:

RESEARCHER - JOHN PRESKILL GROUP

2011 - 2012

• With Prof. John Preskill, Dr. Spiros Michalakis, Dr. Jeongwan Haah at Caltech, proved that a certain class of quantum systems would never function as a form of quantum storage, eliminating their viability in a quantum computer

RESEARCHER – LARGE HADRON COLLIDER (LHC)

Summer 2010

- Analyzed the first data from the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) experiment at the LHC, where the Higgs Boson was later discovered
- Discovered and corrected experimental defects by analyzing Missing Transverse Energy to calibrate experimental setups
- Later received admission to the Ph.D. program in Physics at MIT to continue research on this experiment

RESEARCHER - YORKTOWN HIGH SCHOOL

2007 - 2009

- Developed an assistive aid to help patients with physical disabilities complete exercises
- Device led to an 80% increase in patients' exercise completion rate and a 34% decrease in recovery time
- Won third place in category internationally at Intel ISEF 2009

INVITED TALKS:

- Taro: "Efficiency Tips for Engineers." Youtube.
- **Highlights of Algorithms 2021 (HALG21) Conference:** "BanditPAM: Almost Linear Time *k*-Medoids Clustering via Multi-Armed Bandits."
- U.S. Food and Drug Administration: "An Introduction to Clustering, Multi-armed Bandits, and BanditPAM."
- **Twitch:** "Novel Data Augmentation, Multi-Armed Bandits, and more: New Machine Learning Techniques for Twitch Safety."
- **C3.ai:** "*k*-medoids Clustering and Multimodal Data Augmentation."
- Facebook: "ThreatExchange v2.8 Webinar." Joint presentation. Youtube.
- **Microsoft Security Research Alliance:** "Tracking Advanced Persistent Threats with ThreatExchange." Joint presentation.

ACADEMIC HONORS:

 Stanford Data Science Scholarship 1 of 16 graduate student awardees, University-wide, in cohort 1 of 71 awardees since award inception in 2018 	2022 – 2024
 Stanford Center for Open and Reproducible Science Innovator Prize 1 of 2 University-wide inaugural awardees 	2021
 Stanford Interdisciplinary Graduate Fellowship (SIGF) Full funding for the Ph.D. for 3 years 1 of 33 graduate student awardees, University-wide, in cohort 1 of 295 awardees since award inception in 2008 	2020 – 2023
J.P. Morgan Al Research Ph.D. Fellowship	2020
 Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education (ORISE) Fellowship UnifyID Fellow (Declined) Pear VC Fellow 	2019 – Present 2018 2017 – Present
 NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Honorable Mention Caltech Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF) IBM T.J. Watson Memorial Scholarship Caltech - San Pietro Travel Prize Recipient I. I. Rabi Scholarship Intel International Science and Engineering Fair (ISEF) - Third place 	2013 2011, 2012 2009 – 2012 2011 2009 – 2010 2009
g., (